Alexey Gronskiy

ML Software Engineer / Engineering Manager / TLM

+41 79 845 40 46 alexey@gronskiy.com Zurich, Switzerland LinkedIn: agronskiy ♂ Github: agronskiy ♂ Homepage: gronskiy.com ♂

Profile

As a mathematician, computer scientist, and engineering leader, I have dedicated my career to the advancement of artificial intelligence through both research and practical application. My experience ranges from developing state-of-the-art machine learning systems for code analysis and aviation safety to leading teams in the full cycle of AI product development.

Areas of experise ML for automatic vulnerability fixing (Snyk DeepCode Al Fix $\[mathbb{C}\]$) – Low-memory and low-latency model optimization (quantization, pruning, distillation) – Computer vision for autonomous flight (Daedalean's Spotter $\[mathbb{C}\]$) – Industrial ML research ("Fixing security vulnerabilities with LLMs", co-author $\[mathbb{C}\]$) – Data engineering and orchestration – NN verification and certification ("Concepts of design assurance for NNs", co-author $\[mathbb{C}\]$) – Engineering management, team growth, mentoring.

Experience: 8 years industry (Software Engineering) and 6 years academia (PhD, Computer Science)

Skills, Frameworks and Stacks

- Main languages: C++, Python, Go
- Build & CI/CD: Bazel, Pantsbuild, CircleCI, Github Actions
- ML Training: PyTorch, Tensorflow, DeepSpeed;
 Determined AI, Weights & Biases, Vertex AI
- ML Serving: Huggingface, ONNX, BitsAndBytes/Optimum
- ML Areas: Transformers, U-Nets, ResNets, VAEs; Quantization/Pruning
- Cloud: GCP/AWS, GCS/S3, Firebase

- Data & Formats: PostgreSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Parquet, Kafka
- Deployment & Balancing: k8s, Helm, Terraform, Envoy, Docker
- Observability: Datadog, OpenCensus, Prometheus, Grafana
- Org: Phabricator, JIRA, UML/C4
- Dev: Git, Mercurial, Bazaar, NeoVim, LATEX

Professional Experience

Engineering manager (ML team) Snyk (snyk.io ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 06/2023 – present

- Driving the launch of Snyk DeepCode Al Fix of from Beta to GA via a series of steady model improvements and closing the product-train-eval feedback loop.
- Oversaw development of in-house data labelling service and launched labelling collaborations with external parties, improving the remediation coverage from 1 to 7 programming languages, and increasing the quality by 20%.
- Oversaw moving of ML train/eval and crawling pipelines to automated KubeFlow cloud, speeding up the release cadence.
- Developed services for hosting company-wide ML hackathons and label-a-thons.
- Led and grew a team from 3 to 6 engineers; advised MSc theses (jointly with ETH Zurich).
- Skills & Stacks: C++17/20 (for serving/engine), Python/PyTorch/ONNX (for NLP/LLM), Go (LSP), Bazel, k8s (GKE/Amazon EKS), Helm, Envoy, Docker; production cycle, requirements management, mentoring, people management.

Senior ML SWE, Tech lead Snyk (snyk.io ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 04/2021 – 06/2023

- Together with the team, beta-launched products for automatic vulnerability remediation and code search (Snyk DeepCode Al Fix &), including serving architecture and implementation; worked in a squad across the division set the technical directions, roadmaps and priorities.
- Built the infrastructure for training/evaluation and serving of LLMs for code repair and search (real-time inference of 3B+ models).
 Designed and built internal libraries for simplified storage of various artifacts over any S3-compliant storage.
- Brought in codebase best practices, test-driven development, scaled the experimentation.
- Publications: "DeepCode AI Fix: Fixing Security Vulnerabilities with Large Language Models" (arXiv ♂).
- **Skills:** C++17/20, Bazel; Python/Pytorch/ONNX; Go; k8s (both GKE/Amazon EKS), Helm, Envoy, Docker; Language Server Protocol; Weights & Biases; program analysis.

Senior data engineer SIX Banking Services (six-group.com ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 12/2020 – 02/2021

- Organized technical stack, code review and other processes in a newly established data science unit.
- Performed analytical support of stakeholder business units, provided analysis and computed KPIs for ongoing projects in payment ecosystems.
- Participated in preparatory work for transition to cloud pipelines.
- Skills: Python, Geospatial analysis, Mircosoft Azure (Data Factory, DataLake, Databricks), JFrog Artifactory, data security and compliance.

Machine learning & computer vision engineer Daedalean Al (ddln.ai ♂)

Zurich, Switzerland 06/2018 – 10/2020

- Prototyped real-time visual air-to-air object detection and tracking system, currently Daedalean's core product (Daedalean's Spotter 2).
- Designed and built and in-house model evaluation framework which allowed to automate the release cycle and ablation experiments.
- Shaped out data acquisition and annotation strategies. Defined evaluation metrics, navigated aviation industry standards on operational performance. Supervised interns/MSc students. Carried out flight tests as a fixed-wing aircraft pilot.
- Publications: (with European Aviation Safety Agency) "Concepts of Design Assurance for Neural Networks" (Published by EASA 2).
- **Skills:** C++14, Python, Tensorflow, Git, object detection and tracking, cloud computing and automation (GCP/KubeFlow/Jenkins), technical ownership, requirements design, product development cycle.

Engineering intern Google, Research & Machine Intelligence

Zurich, Switzerland 05/2017 - 09/2017

- Worked on answer ranking module for active question reformulation project. Developed several deep learning models for answer ranking.
- Blog post: "Open Sourcing Active Question Reformulation with Reinforcement Learning" (Google Al blog post ♂).
- Skills: Python, C++11, Blaze (Bazel), Tensorflow 1.x, NLP, experimental design, MapReduce (Flume).

Software engineer ABBYY Software (abbyy.com ☑)

Moscow, Russia 04/2010 - 08/2012

- Worked on a framework (ABBYY Compreno) for automated native language understanding and translation. Designed, developed SDK wrappers for language morphology analysis and text classification.
- Skills: C++03, C#, COM/COM+/WinAPI, SVN, interface design, internal libraries, UML.

Freelance C++ developer

Moscow, Russia 2008 – 2011

- Developed a cross-platform (Mac/Linux/Windows) tool for photo management, sold and maintained it with multiple publishing houses (archive GitHub &).
- Skills: C++03, Qt 4, MercurialHg, PostgreSQL, presentation skills.

Education

PhD in Computer Science ETH Zurich, Dept. of Computer Sience, ML Group

Zurich, Switzerland *2012 – 2018*

- Conducted research in theorectical ML (discrete optimization under uncertainty).
- Launched medical collaborations with University Hospital Zurich.
- Supervised several MSc theses.
- Taught "Introduction to Machine Learning" and "Statistical Learning Theory" courses, created a script for the latter.
- Thesis: "Statistical Mechanics and Information Theory for Approximate Robust Inference" (ETH Dissertation 2)

Specialist in Mathematics Moscow State University, Dept. of Mathematics and Mechanics Moscow,

Moscow, Russia 2006 – 2011

- Specialist (equiv. BSc + MSc) degree in Pure and Applied Mathematics, with Honors.
- Thesis: "On some metrical properties of Boolean functions" (https://gron.sk/msc-thesis ♂)

Languages

• Russian [Native]

• German [Fluent, C2, Goethe]

• English [Fluent]

• French [Fluent, C1, DALF]

Volunteer Work

Firefighter, Emergency Medical Technitian Zurich Fire & Rescue Service

Zurich, Switzerland 2014 – 2021

- Regularly trained as an ambulance assistant (EMT).
- Participated in ambulance shifts during public events in the city of Zurich.
- Was a first responder to alarms from large-scale emergencies.

Hobbies and Other

- Privat Pilot Licence
- Sports (running, cycling, karate)

- Music (flute & guitar)
- Technical blog (gronskiy.com/posts ♂)